<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Gabriel Teles</title>
    <link>http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Gabriel Teles</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 21:39:13 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Github Repository as Maven Repository</title>
      <link>http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/using-github-repository-as-maven-repository/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 21:39:13 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/using-github-repository-as-maven-repository/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://gabrielteles.com.br/images/octocat-repository.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Octocat Repository&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I was working in a project that needed a private Maven Repository since we couldn&amp;rsquo;t expose our artifacts in repositories like &lt;a href=&#34;https://bintray.com/bintray/jcenter&#34;&gt;JCenter&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://search.maven.org/&#34;&gt;Maven Central&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation led me to some possible solutions, which I learned from searching. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if they&amp;rsquo;re the best or if there are easier options, but I&amp;rsquo;ll explain a bit about them and why Github appeared the best to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;creating-an-private-server-running-artifactory:05bb5eb4a1145f415d6af3e318805140&#34;&gt;Creating an private server running Artifactory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jfrog.com/open-source/&#34;&gt;JFrog Artifactory&lt;/a&gt; in the past, with other projects. Since it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;native&amp;rdquo; solution to our problem, I thought first about using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main obstacle to this option is that it has some chances of causing problems in the future. We would have to manage it, upgrade when necessary, control access (!), etc. It somehow runs out of our main devops assignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think if we&amp;rsquo;re a bigger company, this could have been an perfect solution, after all, it cleverly solves this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-jitpack-io-https-jitpack-io:05bb5eb4a1145f415d6af3e318805140&#34;&gt;Using &lt;a href=&#34;https://jitpack.io/&#34;&gt;jitpack.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jitpack is a service that allow you to publish JVM/Android libraries in git (Github, Bitbucket, GitLab, etc) repositories and use them just adding &lt;code&gt;https://jitpack.io&lt;/code&gt; as a maven repository in the project which will consume that artifacts. It has another great features, check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it is also an nice solution. It solves the problem which I&amp;rsquo;ve found on the first option: no more maven repository management tasks. But it let me a bit uncomfortable because to use it with one private repository you have to pay U$9. Yeah, it&amp;rsquo;s a small amount, but between managing Artifactory and paying it, I&amp;rsquo;d rather take first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if you thought the same I did, but one repository is too few! Now I think it&amp;rsquo;s sufficient. We could use one repository to publish all our artifacts and serve them using Jitpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;github-raw-version:05bb5eb4a1145f415d6af3e318805140&#34;&gt;Github raw version&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the &amp;ldquo;anatomy&amp;rdquo; of how maven search for artifacts in given repositories, trying to read &lt;code&gt;http://your-repositorys-url.com/your/artifacts/group/id/pom.xml&lt;/code&gt;, some reading made me try to use &lt;code&gt;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/username/repository/master/&lt;/code&gt; as respository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve got partial success by using it: authentication knocked me down! With public Github repositories, it works like a charm. Private repositories do need HTTP&amp;rsquo;s basic auth, if I&amp;rsquo;m not mistaken. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if it was my or gradle&amp;rsquo;s fault. Even using maven repository credentials, it hasn&amp;rsquo;t worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we needed private hosting, it has not solved our main problem, but gave me some clues!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gradle-plugin-to-rule-them-all:05bb5eb4a1145f415d6af3e318805140&#34;&gt;Gradle Plugin to rule them all&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I&amp;rsquo;ve found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/layerhq/gradle-git-repo-plugin&#34;&gt;layerhq/gradle-git-repo-plugin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;this plugin allows you to add a git repository as a maven repo, even if the git repository is private, similar to how CocoaPods works.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It allowed me to use Github private repositories as Maven repository just by adding &lt;code&gt;git(&amp;quot;https://some/clone/url.git&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;arbitrary.unique.name&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;master&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;releases&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; and following the setup steps described in the readme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than just using git repositories, this plugin adds an &lt;code&gt;publishToGithub&lt;/code&gt; gradle task to generate artifacts, commit and push them to the repository! This 100% solved my problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-happy-end:05bb5eb4a1145f415d6af3e318805140&#34;&gt;The Happy End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I can publish and retrieve Maven artifacts from private git repositories, don&amp;rsquo;t mind about managing maven repository server or even managing permissions, since only our devs and CI environment have access to our Github repository and they can/should access and generate this artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How floats can screw your code</title>
      <link>http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/how-floats-can-screw-your-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 01:20:19 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/how-floats-can-screw-your-code/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pdvend.com.br/&#34;&gt;PDVend&lt;/a&gt; I handle monetary operations everytime and everywhere at our codebase, from our Ruby on Rails API to our client apps. Since money isn&amp;rsquo;t just integer at all, we have a lot of trouble with this. I&amp;rsquo;ll show you some implications of using floats (or doubles) in your code, some situations that you actually can use it and alternatives to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;floats-are-evil:dd275889c84c5fa9cf6dac833d96526d&#34;&gt;Floats are evil&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start trying out Ruby:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-ruby&#34; data-lang=&#34;ruby&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;mi&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;a + b = &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably expect this to output something like &lt;code&gt;a + b = 0.3&lt;/code&gt;. Try to run and you&amp;rsquo;ll see that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;a + b = 0.30000000000000004&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What just happened here? To answer this, we must remember that floats are binary representations of decimal numbers. Not always binary can represent them or it&amp;rsquo;s operations with exact accuracy. Memory is limited, you cannot handle them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about real world examples?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1991, an missile was launched in Saudi Arabia against an american detachment. Another missile called Patriot was going to intercept it. Since Patriot missile battery was on for about 100 hours, it let the timestamps, which where stored as floats, to slowly introduce some diferences from the real timestamp to the computed timestamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remember your physics classes, you can imagine that in order to intercept, Patriot would have to calculate the other missile speed and distance and adjust it direction to the other missile. Speed is measured in distance by time and, since  interceptor missile has some mismatches in time, I think it&amp;rsquo;s not going to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our case, Patriot had about a &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; second of difference in it&amp;rsquo;s timestamp. It means aproximately 600 meters due to it&amp;rsquo;s speed. Float killed 23 soldiers that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read about the case in the U.S. Government Accountability Office &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gao.gov/products/IMTEC-92-26&#34;&gt;Report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;not-that-evil-when-to-use-how-to-use:dd275889c84c5fa9cf6dac833d96526d&#34;&gt;Not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; evil&amp;hellip; When to use? How to use?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Float inaccuracy can be an serious problem in some cases. Is it in all cases?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of programmers only discover about float problems in the day which them have some trouble with it. It happens because, for most cases, some little imprecisions are tolerated. In some cases floats are transformed to integers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This datatype can be used when you can handle small imprecisions, like when there&amp;rsquo;s no problem if your character&amp;rsquo;s HP bar is 0.000000282px to the right or 0.000000013231px emptier than it should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using this datatypes, keep attention to possible errors looking to this points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sums or subtractions (&amp;ldquo;Unsafe&amp;rdquo; operations, due to floating point math)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operations in iterations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code stability (wheter it tent do reduce or magnify errors if floats)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;alternatives-to-float:dd275889c84c5fa9cf6dac833d96526d&#34;&gt;Alternatives to Float&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most languages have workarounds to floats. Here goes some of them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C#: &lt;a href=&#34;https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/364x0z75.aspx?f=255&amp;amp;MSPPError=-2147217396&#34;&gt;decimal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java: &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/7/docs/api/java/math/BigDecimal.html&#34;&gt;java.math.BigDecimal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MikeMcl/bignumber.js&#34;&gt;bignumber.js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PHP: &lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/ref.bc.php&#34;&gt;BC Module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ruby: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ruby-doc.org/stdlib-2.1.2/libdoc/bigdecimal/rdoc/BigDecimal.html&#34;&gt;BigDecimal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another strategy is to simplify your usage of floats. At PDVend, one of the solutions that emerged when we had to resolve float problems with money was to treat all of it as cents, the smallest money unit available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examine what makes senses to your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;conclusion:dd275889c84c5fa9cf6dac833d96526d&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Float is evil, floats can kill, but you can give them a try. You should only keep an eye on your needs and restrictions. Think about what would happen if you have an 0.1 error or an 0.0000001 error; does it matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when you don&amp;rsquo;t use floats, note that your code can implicit &amp;ldquo;create&amp;rdquo; then. PHP, for example, treat some strings as floats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should observe your language nuances, your code stability and your needs for precision when working with floats.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 19:31:48 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://gabrielteles.com.br/blog/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi! This is my new site. If you do not know who I am, please check the &lt;a href=&#34;http://gabrielteles.com.br/about&#34;&gt;about page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I focused in maintaining the simplicity, as you can see. The last website was a bit boring to me, since it was only expositive. Now I plan to bring some content instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also changed some technical details. Now I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&#34;gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was mainly atracted to this options because Hugo let me edit the site super easily. Github Pages was also a good choice, since it&amp;rsquo;s free, &lt;em&gt;really quick&lt;/em&gt; quickstart and keep my site open sourced. It was quite surprising to me how Hugo fits good in Github Pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to integrate some kind of continuous integration, to autobuild the site after commits on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gabteles/gabteles.github.io-dev&#34;&gt;development&lt;/a&gt; repository. (Or it can build automatically every day, to publish the future posts)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that&amp;rsquo;s all folks, keep watching to updates. (:&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>